software engineering radio episode 18
resource management
welcome to a new episode of software
engineering radio in this episode I have
invited guests my name is Michael and my
guest is brush and chain he's working
for IBM Research in Delhi India Prashant
and I have written post our three
together that is a book on pattern
oriented software architecture the topic
of the book is the same as for this
episode it is on resource management
patterns so Prashant what is the
resource in this context and how would
you define it well the resource is
basically any entity that is available
in limited supply and typically you
would like a resource the user for a
resource would be an entity for example
that acquires the resources accesses it
and then finally releases it and on the
other side of it there would be a
resource provider it is basically an
entity that provides a resource many
bits requested by the user could you
give some some example resources that
that would fit and an our scheme sure I
mean resources I mean again there are
since it's such a broad category you can
have all kinds of things regarded as
resources for example memory is a
excellent example of a resource
similarly things like threads file
handles even a processing time of a CPU
is really a resource and the key to note
though is at least in our context we are
talking about resources which are from
the point of view of really IT systems
and we're not talking about like other
kinds of resources because I mean you
can have non IT types of resources also
ok and so where's resource management
really necessary why is that such an
important topic resource management is
boasting necessary really to address the
non-functional requirements I mean such
as for example our performance or
scalability or even like stability and
predictability so I guess resource
management is important that almost
every level video
level the framework application level in
my experience it's also important in
almost every application domain be it
embedded systems or enterprise systems
so the motivation might be different for
those systems for example in an embedded
system you might need first
predictability and stability whereas in
enterprise systems you would mainly
require performance and scalability
exactly in fact it was basically given
that background that we started when we
started this writing this book was a
three what we really did was we actually
looked at existing software systems and
tried to look for patterns we'd actually
mined patterns by analyzing different
systems and we tried to like come up
with a list of generalized patterns so
for example like thread pooling is such
a common thing which is used in so many
system implementations but the pattern
behind it is much more general which is
the same pattern which is used when you
start looking at something like for
example connection pooling and so we
went ahead and we actually looked at
okay what is the fundamental pattern
behind these systems which is really
pooling and that is something which
leverages are like basically best
practices and and that is something that
then we went ahead and we described as a
pattern for resource management and
that's one of the the fundamental
patterns in here ok so how do we start
on on explaining the patterns so I
believe buttons for resource management
really fall into three broad categories
so you talk about patterns that deal
with acquisition of resources and once
you acquire the resources there are
patterns that deal with the life cycle
of the resources and finally there
patterns that deal with how the
resources are actually released back
into the system yes and these patterns
then together form a pattern language
for resource management all these three
categories together would really form
that pattern language for resource
management so I mean just just to maybe
I get started perhaps you should look at
I mean each one of these categories and
look at some of the patterns so I mean
to give you an example let's start with
say
acquisition of resources and let's start
with a very simple pattern and let me
try to motivate one of the most
fundamental patterns by describing an
example so say like you're implementing
system that consists of say several
distributed services and I'll say like
each service
konishi would typically say provide an
interface which will be used by a client
to invoke the service so this is like
such a common scenario but the question
is how would the client actually go
about finding this interface and how
does the client actually find it so that
it could actually use it so couldn't
just a service provider broadcast the
service interface oh yeah sure it could
but then the provider would still need
to broadcast on a periodic basis because
the clients can come and go right so see
the the provider of inherent broadcasted
but there was no client at that time and
the client really came like a little bit
afterwards so again to make sure that
the client actually gets that interface
the provider would then have to
broadcast again which means the provider
really has to broadcast on a regular
basis hmm so couldn't the client just
send broadcast messages saying that it
is interested in a certain service
interface well then again you would have
the same problem because if there's no
provider which exists at the time when
the client is there but the provider
comes on at a later stage so then in
that gives me so the client has to now
periodically broadcast a message saying
that it's looking for a certain
interface plus I mean both like this one
as well as the the one where the
provider is broadcasting both these
approaches really I mean it's leading to
a proliferation of messages in the
network if you really think about it I
mean as a sediment so both these
solutions are really I mean leading to a
proliferation of messages plus it's not
a very elegant solution so in reality I
mean that's where one of the most
fundamental patents comes in which is
the lookup pattern and the look of
pattern is really consists of a lookup
service that allows resource providers
to advertise resources along with
properties that describe these resources
and thus then you have your
actual clients who can then find these
resources using these properties and
then actually go ahead and then use them
the sons like a pretty fundamental
pattern there are many instances where
lookup is used I believe carbon naming
and trading services are really
implementations of lookup if you talk
about Web Services uddi is essentially a
lookup service that allows publishing of
web services and also well it's not so
common anymore but complies in the
concept of the Windows registry is
essentially a lookup service like also
Eclipse Eclipse has the plug-in registry
that holds plugins and extension points
so that is also an implementation of the
lookup pattern yes you're right I mean
in fact as you mentioned there's so many
examples of the capital and in fact it's
really the pattern as well as a lot of
its variants which really formed the
fundamental building blocks of most
distributed systems and speaking of
variants in fact like most patents
lookup can also be implemented with some
variations so for example a very common
variant of lookup is really where are
the resources for example need not be
registered by the resource provider but
it can actually be delegated to a third
party
I mean similarly the the resources can
themselves for example register for the
lookup service those are interesting
variations so let's move on to talk
about the next couple of patterns to
deal with acquisition of resources one
of the most common ones is lazy
acquisition and in general and a general
sense this pattern is applicable to
systems with restricted resources that
must satisfy a high demand such as the
throughput and availability for example
imagine a picture archiving and
communication system and a medical
domain that basically stores patient
data the whole history of the of a
patient and the data includes patient
details of course like address
information
also all the digitized images and a
typical solution how how you would
represent those images would be to
represent them as business objects to
which you attach properties and all kind
of additional information but for a
patient with a long medical history and
several digitized images fetching all
the data all the properties and creating
the corresponding business objects can
take a lot of time the problem here is
how can the picture and archive system
be designed so that the retrieval of
patient information is quick regardless
of the number of images in a patient's
record so generally the goal is to
reduce the initial cost of acquiring
resources in this case the resource is
the memory needed for the business
objects well I mean couldn't you
actually have say several threads which
are loading the images in the background
yes that is one possible solution but
what if the images are viewed only
seldomly it would unnecessarily consume
processing time that might be needed by
other processes so I mean what about I
mean not loading the images at all I
mean why not let the user explicitly
request them yeah well I mean this is
just not actually user friendly I guess
a user would expect that the pictures
are available immediately without having
additional clicks but also on the other
hand the user might not be able and the
screen might just be too small to
display all the images so this leaves
some some options for optimization
so if systems were to acquire all
resources up front a lot of overhead
would be in cured and a lot of resources
would be consumed unnecessarily so the
general solution of the lazy acquisition
pattern this to work resources at the
latest possible time
so the resource is not acquired and
it'll becomes unavoidable to do so and
in our case
when the user really looks at the screen
selected the patient record and wants to
to look at the first image typically you
would introduce a resource proxy that
hides the LaCie acquisition from the
resource user so in our case again we
would have proxies for the images and as
soon as the proxies become viewable
become active because there they are in
the view of the user the system would
load them on demand lazily this would
have essentially saved resources the
typical known use are again the Eclipse
plugins in which cases the descriptor is
loaded on startup but the actual
implementation is then only loaded when
the perspective the view is opened of
that plugin another use case is at hoc
networks and ad hoc networking you have
basically spontaneous interaction with
services and s you can potentially
communicate with with many services in a
network in an ad hoc network you would
load those services those
implementations on demand when actually
needed and would just evict them as soon
as you don't need them anymore the third
use case the third known use I want to
give is just in time compilations
heavily used by Java virtual machines
where the bytecode is just-in-time
compiled instead of interpreted in order
to achieve higher performance and this
just-in-time compilation is not done at
startup for everything but only for the
portions that get actually executed in
fact is it the name itself implies
just-in-time
it's really saying that okay well it's
only gonna happen when it's actually
needed and there again so essentially
what it's doing it's really postponing
it or lazily carrying out the
compilation out of future stage so let
me try to like really summarize
what this pattern is all about as you
described lady acquisition pattern is
really looking at I mean how do you
actually save resources by really
deferring that was their acquisition as
late as possible and not really
acquiring until you actually really need
the resource and by doing this you can
actually I mean save valuable say
processing time or even valuable
resources to make sure that you really
only acquire them when you should need
them so all this is wonderful and as
examples you've given they really
justify why you would want to do it but
sometimes this is not what you may want
to do I mean sometimes you may have
systems or constraints because of which
you cannot really delay the acquisition
of resources until a later stage so for
example systems that need to be highly
predictable in such systems you cannot
really postpone the acquisition of
resources and for really handling such
systems you have a different button
called the your acquisition which
Michael then I would now ask you to
actually go ahead and then try to
motivate and then try to describe yeah
then the ego acquisition pattern is
applicable to systems that must satisfy
a high predictability and performance in
resource acquisition time and that is
useful every time resource acquisition
is expensive and resource acquisitions
for memory or threats and so on are
typically expensive so imagine you have
an embedded telecommunication
application with soft real-time
constraints such as predictability and
low latency and execution of operations
and well in most operating systems
operations such as dynamic memory
allocations can be quite expensive so
memory allocations are protected by
synchronization primitives typically
because you want to ensure that the
available memory accessed acquired from
multiple threats is properly managed for
example the memory management such as
compaction of
all the memory segments that got handed
back on the release of resources need to
be again merged compacted into larger
memory segments and that consumes time
so doing the the management of released
memory blocks and also protecting on
those actions through synchronizations
makes a dynamic memory allocation very
expensive the problem in the embedded
system is how can you achieve
predictable and fast memory allocations
via operations such as a new or meh lock
so you saying basically that the it's
really that the general problem is that
expensive resource acquisitions such as
dynamic acquisition of Lexia threads or
memory so any of these can basically
result in unpredictable time overhead
and so what we're really looking at is I
mean how can you actually acquire
resources from system which have like
soft real time constraints and still I
mean fulfill these constraints so I mean
let me ask you mean so why can't we just
make acquisition itself faster that is a
good idea but in very most cases we had
no impact on the operating system how
that does its memory management how it
optimizes for synchronization and so you
just have no chance to interfere here
and and the typical solution is here to
introduce another layer that basically
uses the ego acquisition pattern and the
solution idea is to equally acquire a
number of resources before their actual
use ideally this time is at the start up
of the system you would acquire the
necessary resources and here of course
you you rely on some estimations or rule
of thumbs how much resources you want to
allocate here and the resources are then
kept in an efficient container from
which you can acquire them later fast
and in a predictable
so coming back to the example you in
this case you would actually implement a
simple memory pool with fixed sized
blocks of memory which gets used only by
a single thread why do I impose those
constraints of fixed size blogs and why
are only forcing of thread well if we
have only a single thread we can avoid
the synchronization overhead because
even if we would manage the resources
ourselves and we would have it access by
multiple threads we would still have
some overhead so we have a memory pool
on a per thread basis that avoids the
synchronization overhead and we use
fixed size blocks to avoid complicated
compaction of use memory blocks the
interesting example of this I just just
thought of it like only we talked about
just-in-time compilers for lazy
acquisition but we also have compilers
that actually do ahead of time
compilation and so this is this command
where they're looking at the JVM for
example they try to a white compilation
overheads during execution so that's I
think an excellent example for eager
acquisition and can you think of like
other examples also other examples are
for example connection and thread pools
which would pre acquire a number of
connections or threads respectively to
serve initial requests quickly okay so
Michael that's very interesting I think
what we've just talked about is lazy
acquisition and eager acquisition we've
talked about I mean how under certain
circumstances you may want to acquire
resources lazily basically push back
that position and under certain
circumstances you want to acquire them
eagerly and so that they're available to
you right at startup time but what's a
third scenario likely is where neither
one of them is sufficient and the
resource acquisition itself is such a
fairly intensive task that you may want
to you may not want to acquire the
entire resource in one go that you may
want to like for example break it
into multiple chunks and this is where a
third button that we talk about in the
category of resource acquisition comes
in which is partial acquisition and you
know not sure what partial acquisition
really describes is this a way of
optimizing your resource management by
breaking up acquisition of resources
into multiple stages and so what you do
is like in each stage you acquire a part
of the resource and so it could be like
dependent upon system constraints such
as how much memory you have based on
that you acquire a certain amount of the
resource or it could also be I mean
availability of other resources on which
you have some dependency and based on
this you basically decide how much you
want to acquire so overall basically
what partial acquisition is talking
about is dividing the acquisition into
stages and then again how many stages
you want to have how much resource you
want to acquire in each stage and all of
these can actually be configured also so
this is what partial acquisition really
talks about given these three patterns
for resource acquisition let's move on
to the second category which is that of
patterns for resource lifecycle
management and there again we have some
very interesting patterns and the first
one let's talk about is caching and
Michel I asked you to go ahead and then
again motivate the pattern yeah caching
is a pretty common pattern for
optimizations the caching pattern is
applicable to systems that repeatedly
acts as the same set of resources and
need to optimize for performance
performance is therefore the main
motivation for this pattern to motivate
a pattern I want to introduce a brief
example in a network management system
you would have many connections open to
the individual network elements that you
are monitoring and the user would
basically look at the elements regularly
on or when there are specific events and
depending on that new connections would
be opened and as soon as the job is done
with this network element he would go
back do something else or just open
the view on another network element here
the critical part is the the regular
opening of connections closing
connections establishing connections
regularly to set of resources but still
on a regular basis we find what you
really owe me nothing understand or try
to like generalize the problem what what
we're really talking about is that like
repetitious acquisition or like say
usage or initialization and then
eventually release on the same resource
I mean that causes a lot of overhead and
so the the real challenge is I mean how
can we actually reduce this occur
repeated acquisition access and release
cost of frequently used resources so
that the performance is not hit but the
question is I mean if that's the case I
mean couldn't you just keep the
references in the application paths yeah
possibly but what about the resource
consumption you would end up maybe with
thousands of open network connection
handles the pattern solution such as to
temporarily store the resources in this
case the connections in a fast access
buffer called cache and you would use
the cache to fetch and return the
resources instead of reacquiring it from
the original resource provider in most
situations this is the operating system
and the cache identifies the resources
by their identity so in in our case it
would be the destination IP address and
and port but it is also common to use a
pointer reference or any or primary key
to identify uniquely and resource and so
coming back to the example you would
implement a connection cache where you
would drop the used connections that you
don't need currently and would just hope
that you don't need to reacquire it from
the operating system establishing the
connection etc the next time you visit a
network element but that you can just
look up
connection in the case that it's still
available not evicted yet from the cache
and so you say processing time and you
avoid unnecessary delays some of the
frequently used variants of caching is
for example a transparent cache that you
as a resource user or application
programmer would not actually notice
that it's in there it would be the
access to the resource provider the
operating system would be hidden by a
proxy and so you don't know actually
whether the resource is allocated
acquired directly from the operating
system or whether the cache kicked then
some heavily optimized saying caches are
read ahead caches and read ahead caches
would guess well if the resource user
wanted to access that resource he might
also want to access this resource one of
the known uses of caching is a web proxy
and the web proxy is a proxy server
located between the web browser and a
web server and the web proxy is
basically accessed the instead of the
web server and it can men cache pages
web pages and returns them when they are
accessed the second time for corporate
net versus 2bic what is done to save on
Internet traffic and and just get faster
access times to web pages another known
use or net data sets where you would
acquire from from the data storage the
data keep it in a data set and then you
can manipulate that data set in your
local cache and as soon as you are ready
you would return or persist the the the
data set again so I believe Michael I
think caching again is a another one of
those fundamental patterns which is used
extensively in most systems that where
for example you know make sure that a
resource is available whenever you need
it and so you basically put it in a like
a fast access buffer which is what we
are calling as a cache and
you can access this resource again at a
later time whenever you need it
and obviously when you don't need the
resource anymore you can always release
it from the buffer so a very very
closely related button to caching is
pooling and there are a lot of
similarities between caching and pooling
and a lot of times there's also
confusion related to whether you want to
use caching or pooling and a pooling is
again it's basically looking at keeping
resources and some kind of a buffer to
avoid having to recycle them but the key
difference between caching and pooling
is the identity of the resources whereas
in the case of caching the identity is
very important because that is what we
use to fetch a specific resource from
this buffer in the case of pooling it
doesn't matter what the weather what
identity these resources have so once
you have used a resource and you release
it to this buffer the resource actually
loses its identity so that it can be
there on when it's fetched again from
this buffer it requires basically a new
identity altogether so typical examples
when you talk about for example thread
pooling or connection pooling the
resources in these cases like threads or
connections these resources don't have
any identity when they're put back into
this this buffer or this pool and so
this is like the the key difference
between pooling and and caching let's
move on to another very interesting
pattern in the area of lifecycle
management of resources and let me let
me talk about the try to like motivate
the pattern by having basically
describing an example so say like again
we have a distributed system that
consists of multiple nodes and let's say
that all the nodes of the system need to
be frequently updated so it could be for
example you want to have some patches
and have these patches be installed in
all the nodes of the system and now
let's assume that if one of these nodes
fails to get updated when you're trying
to do say a patch update then the entire
system basically can enter an
inconsistent state so question is I mean
how do you ensure that whenever you want
to do this
Lord of the patch to all the notes how
do you ensure that either all the nodes
or all the subsystems are successfully
updated or none of them are that is an
interesting problem could each subsystem
communicate with all the remaining
subsystems to indicate that they have
successfully performed an update well
yes I mean that is possible but then
such a point-to-point really
communication among the subsystems I
mean I would actually require that all
subsystems be aware of each other it is
typically not practical I mean also I
mean if you think about it I mean such a
solution really is not scalable I mean
is like the number of subsystems
increases so what's a better way to do
that use the coordinator pattern and so
what the coordinator pattern really is
it's it's an entity that is responsible
for execution and completion of the
complete system update so what we do is
we introduce this component called the
coordinator and then what happens is
that that the task that is to be
performed by each subsystem we split it
up into two parts into two phases the
first phase is really called prepare and
the second one is called commit so in
the first phase coordinator asks each
subsystem to prepare for the work to be
done and if this phase is successful
then the coordinator goes ahead and
initiates the second phase which is the
commit phase which is where the actual
work is done by the subsystems
if the prepare phase fails then the
coordinator basically aborts the task
and asks all the participants are all
the subsystems in this case not to do
anything hold on the sounds almost like
a two-phase commit protocol used in
distributed transaction processing yes
you're right this is in fact the or in
fact that the two-phase commit protocol
is really one of the most well known
examples of the coordinator pattern but
I mean did you realize that coordinator
pattern is it has much more as many more
known uses so for example like in the
case of Java authentication and
authorization service the login context
actually serves the role of a
coordinator
so in like the authentication
authorization service the login modules
are really the participants that are
coordinated by the login context
another very interesting example and
this is actually from the real world is
where a priest actually conducts a
marriage so if you think about the
priest as really a coordinator and the
bride and groom as really the
participants then what actually happens
is in the preparer phase the priest asks
both the bride in the groom if they
agreed to take each other to be their
spouse and only when both of them agree
there's a priest actually commit them to
marriage fascinating I actually like
those real-world known uses they are
they're just so much fun I want to give
also a real-world example for ego
acquisition that we previously discussed
and that is a hamster you know that
little animal and the animal would
typically run around and fetch all he
would find on on fruits and would pack
it into its cheeks basically eager
acquire the food and then go back into
its cage and there it would then have
fast access to its resources to its food
that's that's really a very fascinating
very interesting example yeah but that
is really acquiring resources in this
case Eataly okay so now we talked about
acquisition and access of resources the
third area the third category is
resource release and here we want to
talk about two patterns the first is
leasing prashant do we mind explaining
the leasing pattern so let me try to
motivate leasing with an example so
again let's consider say you have a
service which actually gives you stock
quotes and really forcing it to do is
really get the reference of this service
and that you can find now using our
lookup service the basically lookup
pattern we talked about earlier but now
consider what would happen if this
quarter service or the service which is
giving you stock quotes if that were to
crash and not come up again so the
reference for the
service would be available with a lot of
clients and all these references would
basically become invalid and but these
would still be available why the lookup
service so bottom line is the reference
which was published in the lookup
service that never got removed from the
lookup service the question is how can
we have this reference be automatically
removed as I look up service given the
fact that this service is no longer
available so to really I mean talked
about as a more like as a general
problem is really we are we talking
about
resources that are not used by a
resource user or is basically no longer
available how can we automatically free
such resources so that and make them
available new resource users couldn't
you just have the clients access the
lookup service and and then have the
clients access the stock route service
and let them fail well yes you could but
again you have two problems with it the
first problem is clients which already
have the reference which they got from
the lookup service and they try using it
that that's when they would realize that
this is an invalid reference so it's
it's not a very elegant way to basically
find out that the reference is no longer
valid but a more serious problem is that
that reference is still registered by
the lookup service so even if the
existing clients which have the
reference they figure out that the
reference is invalid what about new
clients new clients is still going to go
up to the lookup service and it will
still get back the same reference which
is now invalid so the basic problem
you're trying to solve is is there any
way by which that reference registered
at the lookup service is automatically
removed because it's now invalid and
this is where the pattern that we are
going to talk about which is leasing
comes into the picture and so the
concept is quite simple we talked about
introducing a lease for every resource
that is held by a resource user so when
a resource is actually granted by in
this case the the grantor and it is
obtained by a holder the lease then
specifies a certain time duration
which the resource user can hold the
resource so going back to our example
the resource user in this case is really
the lookup service because it has been
given a resource which is the object
reference which is it is holding for a
certain period of time now if the
resource itself or if the lease is not
renewed after a certain period of time
then the user should automatically
release that resource so going back to
our example this quarter service we had
the reference registered with the lookup
service if the coded service were to
crash and not come back up its lease
would eventually expire at the lookup
service and if that lease is not getting
renewed by the code of service the
lookup service should then automatically
remove that reference and once that
reference is removed it is no longer
available to the clients and so that
actually helps solve our problem and I
guess it's a pretty interesting question
or tough question actually
who then prolongs lease whether the
resource itself notifies the resource
user or whether the original resource
provider triggers the resource user that
it needs to prolong the lease I guess
there are all kind of variants here
that's correct then you're absolutely
right I mean you can have many of these
different variants and but the bottom
line is one be the one way or the other
you have this concept of lease getting
expired and that resource basically no
longer being valid and needs to be
released and in fact if you think about
there are quite a few known uses of
leasing for example dotnet remoting so
like remote objects in dotnet remoting
are actually managed by so-called
leasing distributed garbage collector
similarly in the case of DHCP which is
like dynamic host configuration protocol
there's a concept of a DHCP lease which
specifies the time for which the server
is granting permission to the client to
use a putter IP address another very
common use of leasing is really for
web-based email accounts so a lot of the
web-based email accounts for example
like MSN hotmail
they become inactive automatically if
they're not used for a certain period of
time and if a user actually uses it
during this period of time then the
lease is automatically renewed so this
is again something which is happening in
the background and you're not explicitly
renewing the release but the fact that
you using the account automatically
leads to the lease getting renewed so as
you can tell them there are quite a few
very interesting are known users of
leasing okay so this has been leasing
one of our two resource release patterns
the other pattern is a Viktor and a
Viktor is a pattern that is also used in
conjunction with other patterns like
like caching and pooling that percent so
what is a Viktor pattern actually about
sure that so Michael as you mentioned a
Viktor or is really used in conjunction
with some of the other patterns we
talked about so let me try to in fact
refer back to one of the descriptions we
were talking about which is that of
caching we said well eventually if a
resource is no longer needed it ought to
be removed from the cache but the
question is when would you know that the
resource should be removed from that
cache or from the buffer so again let me
try to give you another example which is
this the a distributed system where you
have a large number of objects and you
want to keep most of these objects in
memory to be able to access them quickly
but at the same time if you keep too
many of these objects in memory that
again can lead to be like that can be
expensive I mean it can lead to
performance degradation so the question
is it's a fundamental question both in
the early example related to caching as
well as this one how do you decide which
objects to keep in memory so how do you
strike the balance between keeping
objects in memory for efficiency and at
the same time trying to reduce the
number to minimize performance
degradation and this is basically where
we bring in the victor pattern and
really what a victor is we're talking
about again a component which monitors
the use
of resources and then given the use of
resources it then controls the lifecycle
of the resources using one or more
strategies such as LRU and at least
recently used and based on these
strategies the victor selects certain
resources and evicts them or basically
removes them or releases them and going
back to the example we had for in the
case of caching if we had the victor as
a component it would basically monitor
the the use of these resources related
to the cache and it would identify the
the resources which are not being used
as much and it would evict these
resources from the cache and in the case
of pooling so putting again we can have
a similar use we're pooling since we
don't have the identity of the resources
but we are just dealing with the sheer
number of resources in the pool
in the end based on the how many of the
resources are actually getting used we
can actually grow or reduce the size of
the pool and there again when you're
reducing the size of the pool you can
use the victor to really make the
resources okay so we are through with
our patterns on resource management we
went through a list of selected patterns
from the book in the book we have some
more patterns on resource management if
you're interested in more patterns on
resource management we suggest to skim
through the book
prashant anything final to say yes so I
just want to add so as Michael mentioned
first of all this is really a selection
from selection of patterns from the book
but this is again one thing to keep in
mind is patterns as it is pattern
languages is always it's an ongoing book
so they're likely to be additional
patterns related to resource management
that either we may discover or others
may discover but what's interesting to
again notice that broadly speaking you
the patterns really fall in these three
categories and as we discover more
patterns we would like to hear back from
listeners too so that we can again
update this pattern language and to make
it much more
comprehensive okay so thanks Bachand
for joining us for the show and bye-bye
bye-bye thanks
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning party for providing the music as
well as Lipson comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]